Why do we become mediocre? The first one
is deniability. What we end up with is
saying I am attached to coming up with
an idea that everyone is going to love,
being reassured that nothing bad is
going to happen. If I can be guaranteed
those two things, then I'll go do it.
And that's why most people would rather
be mediocre.
>> My guest today is Seth Godin. [music]
You're going to hear how Seth survived
800 rejection letters in a single year,
and that led him to now writing 21
books, multiple best sellers. We're
going to steal his self-belief so that
you can use it for yourself today.
>> Winners are actually quitters, as long
as it's strategic quitting.
>> Quitting isn't failing. What's failing
is sticking with something that's not
working and not making me happy.
Quitting is a chance to invest in the
thing that I ought to be doing next.
>> Is there like one single belief that
helps to cure mediocrity in most people?
>> Well, I have a mantra, which is
>> I want to talk about your insane work
ethic, which I've admired for so many
years. You've published a blog post
every single day for I believe 26 years,
often two to three times a day. That's
as like some public math, 10,000 posts,
maybe more than 3 million words. It kind
of puts you among like the most prolific
creators, I think, of all time. Picasso,
you know, Casey Neistat with his
millions of videos, if you want to go a
little bit more more common, Beeple, 17
years of daily art. I guess my first
question is, what does hitting publish
every single day teach you, and why do
you do that?
>> I don't think of
a work ethic being like this. I have a
craft ethic. I have a posture of sharing
the work cuz I think it's worthwhile.
And the thing is, I made a decision
once,
and then I don't have to make it again.
So, there's going to be a blog post for
me tomorrow, not cuz it's the best blog
post I ever wrote, but because it's
Thursday.
And that changes everything, cuz if you
know there's going to be a blog post
tomorrow, when you go to sleep tonight,
that's what you're going to be thinking
about.
Habits create who we are.
And what I found was re-litigating
each decision was enervating, was
undermining me.
But if I can show up and say, "This is
my craft. Here, I made this."
then it becomes who I want to be.
>> Yeah. Like I I I guess
let's say there's somebody listening
right now, and this somebody could be me
on many days. But, you know, when you
don't want to do something, like you
have that deep in your veins, please,
like I would rather do anything else in
the world except the thing I know I need
to do. What would you tell them, or what
do you tell yourself?
>> Well, I think it's helpful to break it
into pieces, right?
Is it common for you
to not want to do the thing you have to
do? Cuz if that's the case, then it's
not the thing, it's the have to part
that you're
right? That people will go on vacation
and do things that they just paid a lot
of money to do that are supposed to be
fun, but if that was their job, they
would hate it.
So, that's part of what's going on here.
And we can talk about what are the
trades we make to solve problems, what
are the trades we make to create the
thing we want to build.
Or it could be that you're in
engaging with something toxic.
And there's something in your system
that's saying, "Don't do that."
And I had a young friend who took karate
lessons. And after 3 weeks, he said,
"They yell at me and they hit me."
Now,
some people think that's fine. He did
not.
Don't take karate lessons.
Right? If it's making you sick to
negotiate to win in certain settings,
small claims court or whatever it is,
then don't, because you only get
tomorrow once. You don't even get get a
chance to do it over again.
We have more freedom than we want to
admit. So, how are you going to spend
the resources you've got and what are
you going to get in return?
>> It's really good because you've also
talked about like there's a couple of
quotes from one of your last books. I
think it was The Dip. Where it's you
talk about most people are afraid to
quit and that and you say winners are
actually quitters as long as it's
strategic quitting. When do you know
whether to quit or not and what does
that mean?
>> So, you've talked about this a lot in in
podcasts and books and things.
The
you're not wearing a tutu even though
you took ballet lessons when you were
six.
And you're not still wearing your Boy
Scout uniform even though you were in
the Boy Scouts. You've quit things many
times in your life. Everyone listening
to this.
But the whole Vince Lombardi nonsense of
winners never quit makes absolutely no
sense.
That what we need to do before we start
a project is realize there's going to be
a hard part. That's why it's worth
doing.
Never quit at the hard part. Either quit
before you start
or quit after the hard part. But see
that the hard part is coming. All right,
with that said, then we look at our
life, our future, our assets and we say
based on who I am and where I am and the
way the world is,
ignoring the sunk costs, ignoring how
much it cost me to get here, if I was
going to make a new decision today,
what makes sense to me?
Right? So, in the case of my blog,
I could quit my blog anytime I want.
The fact that I've done 10,000 blog
posts is a gift from the old me.
I don't have to accept the gift. I can
say, "No, thank you. That's not serving
me anymore."
And being willing to forgive that past
self, refuse that past gift and say,
"Quitting isn't failing.
What's failing is sticking with
something that's not working and not
making me happy. Quitting is a chance to
invest in the thing that I ought to be
doing next."
>> Yeah.
You know, it's interesting because that
idea of not quitting at the hard part is
so crucial because on the other hand of
having every right to quit when you want
to, you have also, I believe you got 800
rejection letters from book publishers
over over Yeah, in one year. Eight 800
That's like impressive almost. Now
you've written 21 best-selling books?
>> Yeah.
>> And so, you know, I guess my question
there is like
what do you tell yourself to keep going
when you've got a bruised ego and you
want to give up?
>> Yeah. Well, so many people who are
listening or watching to this
try really hard and are on the edge of
hustling. Mhm. I don't like hustling and
I want to explain what I mean by
hustling and about the letters because
this whole rejection Olympics thing and
keep hassling people until they say yes,
that's not what this is about.
What happened 800 times in a row is
someone in New York publishing bought a
stamp, put it on an envelope, and mailed
me a letter that said no.
That's a big thing that they had to do
to reject me.
The thing was two. One, it's their job
to look at book proposals. I wasn't
spamming people. I wasn't hassling
people. If I people like me didn't
exist, they would be out of work. It's
their job.
And number two, my rejections kept
getting better.
That the beginning first few were no.
By the time 6 months had rolled around,
it was this isn't going to work for us
right now, but would you consider doing
something like this? That people saw
that I was listening and I was there to
serve them.
So this is a key distinction. You're not
asking for a favor when you're selling
something. You're not asking for a favor
when you engage with someone. You are
offering them something.
And if they you're not offering people
something of value, listen to them
and go build a thing that is actually
valuable for them cuz it's got to be
voluntary or it's not going to work.
>> That's such a great point because
today's world there is a lot of uh
rejection porn that basically, "Oh, I
you know, I pitched a thousand investors
and they all said no." But the part that
they leave out is when why you get the
yes is the iteration.
>> Right.
>> Right? It's no, I listened to you. We
had a conversation even though it was
mostly in my head and I took your
feedback. I implemented I got better. So
by the end of the thousand it wasn't
they all suck, it was I got better. Is
that right?
>> Yeah, and it doesn't have to be
interacting with the same person over
and over again. You learn so much from
all the people who walked by your store
and didn't come in that you changed the
window. And as soon as you changed the
window someone came in and said, "Oh, I
should do that more." So we get what we
measure.
And the feedback loops are super
important because if you're measuring
the wrong thing. So if you go to the gym
and you see someone on one of the
Stairmasters and they put their hands on
the side rails and to lift their weight
up, why did they do that? It hurts your
back. It doesn't give you a good workout
cuz it makes the little number on the
Stairmaster go up. That's the only
reason. Is that why you went to the gym?
To make the number on the Stairmaster go
up? Cuz if so, you succeeded.
When we measure things that don't
matter. If we're busy counting calories
but not losing weight, did we count
calories cuz we like counting calories
or did we just learn something about our
metabolism and maybe we're counting the
wrong thing?
So if you want to get funded
and people who care enough to listen to
you are saying no,
can you imagine why they might be right?
The answer they're an idiot is not
acceptable.
Why might they be right to reject me?
Cuz everyone
who makes a decision is correct based on
who they are, what they believe, what
they want, and what they heard from you.
Every single time they are correct. And
if you want a different answer, you need
to tell a different story and create
different conditions for that to happen.
>> That's a great point, and really
counterintuitive to what we actually
think in our head.
>> Right.
>> Because typically rejection's painful,
so you build up a little armor of no's,
and then you get on the defensive about
why they're the idiot.
>> Right.
>> But I I love that because you say
actually that feedback loops are the
secret to improvement. And so, breaking
this down practically, how could I
listening today
take a feedback loop and make my life
better? Which I loved you had in the
book, your most recent book The Knot.
There's a lot about feedback loops in
there and how important they are. So,
can you tell us tactically, how would
you use a feedback loop to get better
every time?
>> The first thing I would say is who gave
you the feedback loop you're using.
Who's benefiting from that? Mark
Zuckerberg?
Cuz Mark Zuckerberg wants you to have a
feedback loop of likes and what people
are saying about you in the comments.
Because if he can get you hooked on
that, you will work for free and his
advertisers will have something to buy.
Right? If you're on YouTube, is the
feedback loop the number of views cuz
the easiest way to get a lot of views is
to do something horrible and it'll
attract a crowd. Is that why you're
here? Well, that's what YouTube would
like you to measure. That's why they
made the number easy.
And so, when you know, I I give advice
to friends who are authors and like,
"All right, but I want to make the best
seller list." Why?
Like, what would it mean to be on the
New York Times best seller list? Cuz I
can tell you how to do it for $65,000.
There are people who have to
books on there, paid money to game their
way onto it. Is that what you want? What
do you get if that happens? So, let's
get very clear about what we get for
when we put in the effort
to do something. Cuz that's what when
we're solving a problem, what we're
doing is we're making an exchange. We're
leaning in, doing effort, and getting
something in return. But if you're
measuring what's easy, if you're
measuring what your friends are
measuring,
then you're going to get stuck. So, I
live north of New York City, and when we
used to go to the movies,
I noticed it.
Many of the teenagers looked the same.
This was before the internet. Like, how
did they know how to dress?
And if I finally figured out, they all
look like Barbie.
And that was their method of saying I'm
an insider.
But when we talk to kids in high school,
they're all unhappy.
>> Mhm.
>> So the thing they're measuring, which is
how can I hang out with the the cool
kids and look all the same, is actually
not the thing that's getting them what
they want. But it's super easy and
there's all this pressure to measure the
wrong thing.
So where I began is, let's get clear
about who it's for and what's it for.
And what are we going to get out of
this? And then how do we measure more of
that?
>> Seems like it's taking a lot of mental
pauses to ponder, which is not that
normal. And actually asking yourself, is
this a mimetic desire that I have
because somebody else has it, or is this
like a deep desire?
>> Right.
>> And so what I want to talk a lot about
today is getting unstuck, cuz I see a
lot of people in their way. And I think
this book is a guidebook for that. But
maybe I'd ask one more question first
about
how can you tell if a desire that you
have is yours or somebody else's?
Because you have so many things that are
quote unquote weird for for normal life.
You have a lot of boundaries that you
put on that would be against normal
success. So maybe you could teach us how
to do that.
>> Two words.
High school.
>> Mhm.
>> When in doubt, look at high school.
>> High school is where we got
indoctrinated. Indoctrinated to get a
job at a famous company. Indoctrinated
to do what the boss says. Indoctrinated
to say, "Will this be on the test?" Over
and over and over again. The
hierarchies, the status, the
affiliation, it's about high school.
And if high school life is making you
happy as an adult, please don't change
it in any way.
But if you find that you are rehearsing
those indoctrinations,
it could very well be that someone else
is benefiting from that, the local
insurance company, the local real estate
broker, whatever, whatever, cuz you're
fitting in all the way,
and not you.
And yeah, it takes a lot of guts to take
a deep breath and say, "No, no, no.
That isn't giving me joy.
And I'm going to pay attention to what
these people think of me, and I'm going
to ignore those people."
And when we were talking about
rejection, one of the most powerful
things an entrepreneur, a salesperson, a
creator, an artist has is a simple
sentence, which is "Thank you, it's not
for you."
It might be for somebody. You should
make something for somebody,
but if someone rejects you because they
are left-handed and you're making
right-handed scissors, you don't try to
persuade them to become right-handed.
You say, "Thank you, but it's not for
you."
And this is what a successful stand-up
comic does. They don't fly to Italy and
yell at people who don't speak English.
They want to work a room with people who
are there to hear them.
So, let's take a deep breath and say,
"All right, what is important to me, and
why is it important, and how much of
this is about high school, and how much
is this about becoming the person I want
to be?"
>> It's interesting. Right now, I think
even in what what I do, I think about
this a lot because when you have a a lot
of attention on the internet,
um you can get really caught into mass
people-pleasing, you know? And and I
hear this a lot from from people who
work for me. Like, I'm a people-pleaser.
Seems to be a common thing that people
say.
And one of the tools that you have, I
think, to get out of the way of if you
are a people-pleaser,
is personal statements. I loved your
framework for how you think about
personal statements.
And I'm curious, how would you start
writing a personal statement, which
seems to be a way to get unstuck and to
make sure you're not stuck on something
you shouldn't even be doing in the first
place?
>> Yeah. So,
mission statements, elevator pitches,
what a waste. No one ever bought
anything on an elevator.
You don't need an elevator pitch.
>> It's true.
>> And if you look at giant corporations,
their mission statements are all
interchangeable and they mean nothing.
And they're hiding the truth. And the
truth is we're here to make money.
And all you got to do is like look at a
drug company. Which drugs did they bring
out? Which ones did they not bring out?
It has nothing to do with their mission
statement. It has to do with what made
the bosses money. So, be honest about
it. And now we can make decisions. So,
purpose is what's the one thing?
What's the one thing I'm trading my time
for right now? What's the one thing I'm
taking risk for right now? The one thing
if it happened
that would be good.
And it's a trap to say money.
Because yes, you need enough. Enough
might be a very big number.
But all money is is a tradeable thing, a
code, a number, a rank. Money itself
isn't why you're doing anything.
Once you have enough.
So, what is it? Who are you trying to
please? Who are you listening to? You
know, I was walking on Columbus Avenue
on the Upper West Side. This was only 10
years ago, so I was 50-something. And as
I'm walking, there's a small playground
there. And I hear some 7-year-old
taunting some other kid. Like really
taunting in an angry sing-song voice.
And I looked over to see if the other
kid was okay.
And I realized the 7-year-old was making
fun of me.
He was harassing me cuz I was bald. He
was harassing me.
And I got to tell you for like 3 minutes
after that I felt bad.
I felt like oh, how did I let this
person down? What What did I do wrong?
Should I have been wearing a hat? And
then I went wait.
Number one, he's 7. Number two, I don't
know him. Number three, I didn't make
any promises to him that I haven't kept.
I forgive you. You're You're going up to
be a bully and I can't fix that.
But, how do I insulate myself? My blog
has no comments. I don't know the stats
of my blog. I don't know how many people
read my blog. I don't know how many
books I sell.
Why? Cuz nothing about that would make
my life better.
I haven't read a review of my books on
Amazon in 10 years.
>> That's crazy.
>> Because tell me the truth, you're an
author.
>> Yeah.
>> Did reading the reviews make your next
book better?
>> No. [laughter]
>> Right, of course not. And are you going
to write the first book again? No. So,
why are you reading the reviews? You're
reading the reviews cuz of high school.
That what you're doing is going back to
their people talking about me behind my
back in the ladies room. I can go listen
to what they're saying.
Is that helping you?
And so, you know, the mindset of turning
your life into an art project where you
are creating generous work for other
people,
if you're generous enough, you're going
to get paid.
And where you're keeping track of what
works for you, and ignoring relentlessly
ignoring what doesn't work. That's not
easy, but you only have to decide once.
That's where your purpose statement
comes in, which is to say, "Oh, thank
you for that feedback, but I'm looking
and you're not on the list of people I
care about feedback from. Have a great
day."
>> That's so true. I was literally going to
tell you earlier how proud I was of all
the reviews we got for the book. So,
that is actually hysterical.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh but you're right. It actually didn't
make the second book better. And I think
a lot of people in life, you know, if
you just do performance art as opposed
to art, that can that can wear on you
pretty quickly. But the other side that
you talk about a lot in the book and
sort of overall in all of your work is
idea of mediocrity.
>> Mhm.
>> And
you refer to uh the four horsemen of
mediocrity as deniability, helplessness,
contempt, fear.
And so, I'm curious. One, tell me about
the four horsemen. And then two, how can
we figure out which one of those is
crippling us?
>> Right. All right, first first let me
the word mediocre just means average.
And there two kinds of mediocrity
and compromise.
And so let's I want to talk about
compromise first because compromise
isn't exactly the same thing.
If you
are an architect and you have a client
and you bring your perfect building to
them and they ask you to make changes to
it so it will work better for their
business, that's a useful compromise.
That's a powerful compromise.
On the other hand, if you bring an idea
to someone who doesn't want to change,
who doesn't want to they will insist
that you sand out all the edges and make
it banal, that's a bad kind of
compromise. That's the kind of mediocre
we're avoiding, right? To make it so
that every single human doesn't notice
us so we don't get criticized.
All right, so then we got indoctrinated,
we got a job. Why do we become mediocre?
The first one is deniability.
Deniability means
you don't have to put your name on it
cuz it's what everyone else was doing.
And this one is super common, right?
The next one is this idea of contempt,
which is I don't care that much about my
job. I don't care about that much about
my customers. It's just not worth it.
Anytime you hear someone say, "I'm just
doing my job."
it's cuz their bosses burned any
relationship they have with what they're
doing. It's not their fault. They're in
a system that doesn't want to reward
what they're doing, right? And
we can go down a list of many other
ones, but what we end up with is saying
I am attached
to coming up with an idea that everyone
is going to love
and
to being reassured that nothing bad is
going to happen.
If I can be guaranteed those two things,
then I'll go do it.
And that's why most people would rather
be mediocre. Most people would rather
stay in the middle cuz those guarantees
are not on the table.
And when we see
someone do a live act,
the odds that this is going to be the
best performance they ever gave are
zero.
You can't have the best one you ever
gave unless you have some that aren't
the best ones.
You have to be okay with that, or else
you're just going to phone it in. You
have to make these choices. Is the work
I'm doing
generous enough?
So, when you I talk to emergency room
doctors, surgeons, how can you do this
after the first patient died? How do you
go back to work?
And the answer is because someone is
going to go and help this person.
Is it always going to work? No, but
that's the price. The price we pay to
show up to help people is sometimes it's
not going to work and the
fatal consequences.
You and I don't have to deal with that.
Right? What a treat then. We get to do
something I get to do a blog post. It's
might be the worst blog post of the
year. Maybe even of the decade. It's not
fatal.
I'll be back tomorrow.
>> You are arrogant, you are lazy, and
you're stupid. If you're sitting there
and you cannot afford super cars, you're
one of those three.
>> [music]
>> You should work 84 hours a week. No
family, no kids, no girlfriend. Every
day you wake up, the only thing that
should be on your mind is money.
>> That's not what being rich looks like.
[music] Jeff Bezos is worth $257 billion
because of Amazon. He drinks coffee and
reads the newspaper in the morning. Tim
Cook earned $74.3 [music]
million at Apple last year. He turns his
phone off to go to the gym. Berkshire
Hathaway is worth [music] $1.3
trillion. Warren Buffett founded it with
his best friend. You don't have to wake
up at 3:00 [music] a.m. every day. You
don't have to give up your life, and you
definitely don't have to do it alone.
The goal was never a business you run.
It's a business that runs without you.
It's time to take back control of your
business and your life. [music] Come do
it with me on September 18th. I'll see
you there.
I feel like when you can when you can
diagnose what you're doing, it's so much
easier to fix it. And half the time we
know that something's wrong, but we
can't diagnose what it is, why it's
happening. And so, it's not just that
we're stuck and we're lazy and whatever.
It's It's we actually just haven't been
able to figure out what the disease is.
So, we're trying all the vitamins and
you know, don't realize ah, it's
actually just get outside, get some sun,
take a walk. You don't need a vitamin.
And so, um I really like this. I think I
don't know if this is too
particular of a question. But is there
like one single belief
that helps to cure mediocrity in most
people? Like if you believe in this, you
can cure this desire to just play it
safe and be mediocre?
>> Well, I have a mantra, which is work
that matters for people who care.
And it has two parts. You have to start
with the second part.
Only for people who care.
You have to ignore the people who don't
care.
All right. Among the people who care,
what would matter to them?
Can I do something that would matter to
them? So, let's say you have a job in a
big company
and you're feeling stuck. And I can talk
about why that might be, but you say I
don't have any agency, I don't have any
freedom.
I just have to do what they tell me to.
And I ask you the following.
Would you get fired for starting a book
group
once a week over lunch on Fridays? Six
people. Probably wouldn't get fired for
that.
Could you pick five people who would
really like to be in that group?
If you organize that group, would your
life get better?
Work that matters for people who care.
Because guess what happens? After the
book group's working really well, the
next time they need a little project
done, they'll ask you if you want to do
it cuz you just demonstrated you could
make this thing work. And then the next
thing. And then the next thing. That we
get freedom by using the agency we deny
we have well so that the people around
us will give us more.
>> It's really precious in this day and age
kind of with how society is and the
infrastructure and you have a quote
that I love from your blog which is the
industrial age brought compliance and
compliance brought fear and fear brought
us mediocrity.
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> What do you mean by this?
And what can we do about this?
>> So what's the industrial system? If you
have a car
the reason it doesn't cost $6 million is
cuz it's not made by hand. It has
interchangeable parts. It was made in a
factory. And the fact is you can go get
a you know a little wireless lab now for
$99 that should cost a million dollars
but it's made in a factory.
Factories are about repetitiveness and
they are about compliance. So we had to
build public school. You can look in the
public the history of public school.
Public school was built by factory
owners to train people to do what they
were told.
And the way we get people to do that is
we give them prizes, weekly salary, and
then we threaten them with punishment,
fear.
Do what I say or you're out the door.
And so you're on the assembly line
faster and faster and faster repeating
what you did yesterday. An assembly line
doesn't have to like Charlie Chaplin
putting together a car. If you're doing
insurance claims, you're on the assembly
line.
And there's one reason why AI is
freaking so many people out cuz AI is
eager to go into the assembly line doing
the same thing over and over again. So
we got factories that create value and
then we got fear as the the
weapon that they use which leads to
compliance. And compliance is all about
how do I fit in the middle so they don't
notice me.
And that cycle built our culture. It
made us all the richest people in the
history of the world but it also created
all sorts of pain and suffering cuz
that's not what human beings were born
to do.
>> It's interesting. It makes me think of
leaders versus managers.
>> Mhm.
>> Um you know, I'm a leader at our company
and I've been a manager at other
people's company before and it is
actually quite hard even as a leader, I
think, to not fall into the salary plus
you could potentially get fired
trap. You know, it's not only like when
you are subjugated to it, you're part of
the system. You then become that type of
leader and you almost have to fight, I
feel like your inherent desire to just
be complied with and have people do what
you want them to do as a leader. And so
you draw really important distinctions
between managers and leaders. What makes
the difference between a manager and a
leader?
>> So, you are
uh
the leader of your company, but lots of
companies don't have a leader, they have
a manager.
They're not the same thing. Managers use
power and authority
to get people to do a job they know can
be done.
So, we need managers at hotels, at fast
food restaurants. Someone to make sure
that the subway's running on time,
that's management.
Leadership is voluntary.
You can't require people to follow you
as a leader cuz if you do, you're a
manager.
Leadership is I'm going over there, who
wants to come?
Leadership is this might not work.
So, in your career as an independent
thinker and writer and podcaster and
investor,
you have done many, many things that
weren't in the playbook.
And your
value add is not that you are a boring
manager who does
Goldman is filled with people like that.
Your value add is you are willing to go
to a frontier and do things that might
not work. And so, people choose to
follow you.
And so, if you are running a business
where management is important, you're
going to have to figure out how to run
an industrial business where you get
people to comply. I'm glad the pacemaker
company, if you have a pacemaker, has
six sigma with compliance. It's not
like, oh, we did our best, but it was
Thursday. No, they they really nailed it
down.
But if you want change to happen,
you're going to need to lead. And you do
that by creating the conditions for
enrollment, creating the conditions for
possibility, so that people choose to go
on this journey.
And then, when it's time for the
business to be managed, you should
probably sell it.
>> Interesting. You you have a saying,
"Managers want authority, leaders want
responsibility."
My question is, what is the first step
you can take to become a leader and not
a manager?
>> The most important thing is to lead
yourself.
And we have a lot of trouble with that.
And what The Not is about is
you know, many of my books have been how
do you get other people to change their
mind. This is about how to get yourself
to change your mind.
And how do you figure out how to be more
curious? How do you figure out how to be
more resilient? How do you figure out
how to measure what matters? Cuz once
you start doing that,
you will begin to move. And when you
will begin to move, then people who want
to move will begin to follow you.
And
you know, I love the Main Street model
of boring, small, recession-proof
businesses.
Most of what makes them boring
is on the outside, they're not looking
for innovation. Right? If I need my lawn
mowed, I just want it mowed. I don't
need you to be innovative.
But on the inside, there's huge value
add if you can figure out how to
innovate, how your employees engage with
each other and with the customers.
Those sorts of shifts
are critical, and this is what it means
to be a professional. What it meant to
do hard work 100 years ago, where you
needed to change your clothes twice a
day cuz you were digging ditches.
We're so lucky we don't do that anymore.
Um at least I am.
Okay, so what's the hard work?
And the hard work isn't like gritting
your teeth and getting through it. The
hard work is being clear with yourself
and then your team about the change you
seek to make. What is the purpose of
what we're doing? So, if you look at
Will Guidara and Danny Meyer and talk
about hospitality, hospitality doesn't
come naturally at the end of a 6-hour
shift.
It's the work.
That's what we're talking about. Where
is the work?
>> It's really underrated and hard, too,
because
you know, I think in this day and age we
use Slack so much in my company, for
instance, which is a great way to remove
all emotion and just have sort of
compliance top-down leadership.
>> Yep.
>> And I always try to go back to the quote
that's, you know, if you want to teach
your people how to build a boat, don't
teach them about nails and ropes and
bindings, teach them to yearn for the
vast and endless sea, which is some
saint that I can never remember, but I
should remember because I quote it a
lot. And I think your work does a really
good job of that. It's like we want to
inspire people and ourselves,
uh not just mandate things. Like I know
you famously don't like the word should,
too, which I think is probably
important. I know you've said optimism
is a choice
and a tool.
>> Right.
>> I can sometimes be proud of the fact
that I'm a realist, and that could even
border on the on a pessimist take.
I'd be curious your stance.
How do we switch to optimism? How do you
have a choice to be optimistic? How
could we do that if somebody's stuck
being really pessimistic?
>> Well, so, Cody, this is the first thing
you've ever said to me that wasn't true.
You're an optimist, and that's
a key
to
uh what you've built.
You're not a a foolish optimist. You're
not saying, "I'm going to invest in this
company and hope it's going to go well."
Like what we want is when we're making a
decision like, "How do I invest
$100,000?" We want to put on a pessimist
hat
and say, "In this moment, let me make a
list of all the things that could go
wrong. Let me be very clear about the
possible failure points." All right.
But, the only way you're going to go
forward is once you've established a
foundation,
is to say, "Now, how do I act as if?
How do I set this up in such a way that
if things work,
we're going to get
even more of where we want to go."
So, the problem with doomscrolling,
naysaying, and pessimism as a habit is
you talk yourself into mediocrity again.
You talk yourself into deniability. You
talk yourself into a future that you
don't want to end up with.
And so, when I say that optimism is a
tool,
it's simply to say,
"When I'm going to make a decision,
the first thing I want to do is put my
pessimist hat on to make sure I'm not
going to be out of the game.
But, then my optimist hat says,
'Where are the chances to lead? Where
are the chances to create value here?'
But, if you're fully a pessimist, you're
never going to think through those
things.
>> Yeah, and I think if you're fully a
pessimist, you're not going to ever get
unstuck because you won't take action,
which requires optimism. And and I I
like the way you framed it in the knot
about um
confusion is often in the way of moving
forward. It's not just pessimism, but
you know, you talk about the conspiracy
of stuck is built on basically three
confusions. And the confusions being
short-term conflict avoidance,
unwillingness to create tension,
misunderstanding of risk. What are those
and how do you fight these types of
confusion?
>> Yeah, okay. So, short-term conflict
avoidance is something that I'm glad we
have in our culture.
Right? Someone cuts you off in traffic,
you don't ram their car. That we don't
we've been calloused recently with all
the spam phone calls and all the people
hustling us to
be confronted all day long with this,
but for 10,000 years human beings were
generally kind to each other. And so,
when we need to speak up to get unstuck,
the easiest thing to do is not bring it
up at the dinner table, not bring it up
with your parents, something that's been
going on for too long, not bringing it
up because in for 1 minute it will be
awkward. So, we just live with it for a
very long time.
So, that's why the word short-term is
there. That
it's worth having a short-term conflict
if it leads to long-term benefit to both
sides. Just say it.
The second one is about the
unwillingness to create tension. Tension
and stress are different. Stress is bad.
Stress
wears us out. It leads to trauma.
Tension is pulling a rubber band back
before you let go. If you don't pull it
back, it's not going to fly across the
room.
So, when Taylor Swift says
tickets are going to sell out in 20
minutes, she just created tension for
everyone in the room. Because if you
don't buy a ticket right now, you're
going to get left out. So, when we show
up to lead, when we show up to create
possibility, when we get unstuck, we're
going to cause tension for other people.
We inflict it on purpose. We willingly
inflict tension. Your book comes out in
September. When people know that,
there's tension that exists until they
pre-order it. Because you invented that
tension, right? And then
what we know is we
are terrible at being rational about
risk. People
still buy uh
insurance before they get on an
airplane. Airplanes never crash. It is
way more dangerous to drive to the
airport than to fly to wherever you're
going. But it feels more dangerous to be
on a plane.
And we hesitate to ask our boss
something that's mutually beneficial cuz
it feels super risky. Even though in the
history of this organization, not once
has it ever led to someone's career
ending, but it feels risky.
So,
when people show up and they're making
huge progress through an industry, it's
usually
not because they have more skill than
you, but but they're better at
understanding what's actually risky
versus what feels risky. Public speaking
is not risky. It just feels risky. So,
people like you and I can go on stage
and give a speech because everyone else
thinks it's too risky.
No,
it's risky to work in a coal mine.
>> You know what's crazy, too? I've been in
a coal mine, oddly, and even that risk
now has decreased so hugely. Not to
mention how much they get compensated
for it, and I was worried about black
lung and all of these things that kind
of don't exist anymore. Now, granted,
it's much riskier than me and my
spreadsheets, you know, but um there's
even a perceived risk there that's huge
that isn't real. I've been obsessed with
this idea lately because I think you
can't spell rich without risk. Like, if
you want to make money, I don't know
anybody who can do that for you with no
risk. And if if they can, they probably
keep that secret to themselves.
But, it seems like our entire society is
set up to not have risk. You know, even
now, you know, younger people getting
married less, having sex less. Some of
that's good, perhaps, but also it's just
like tamping down our risk spectrum.
So, I wonder,
like, for somebody who's sitting there
and worried about taking on more risk
and putting themselves out there, what
do you say to them, or what do you
repeat to yourself when you're like,
"This feels risky. I'm going to do it
anyways."?
>> The way you learned how to walk and the
way you learned how to talk,
and almost everything that's important,
is you did it a little.
You discovered what happened, and then
you did it some more, and you got good
at it.
Please don't quit your day job. Don't
quit your day job. Go try to mortgage
your house, risk your life savings.
Don't do that, right? But, maybe on
Saturday go to a garage sale,
buy $18 worth of stuff and see if you
can sell it on eBay.
Is that risky?
I don't think it's risky. I think it's
generous because there's somebody in
Toledo who wants that thing you found.
And they're eager to pay for it and
you're going to charge them less than
it's worth.
And there was someone in the garage who
wanted to sell it to you and they're
eager to sell it and you paid what they
thought was and you came out ahead by
creating value for people.
So, when people talk to me about risk,
I ask them things like this. Like, when
was the last time you did something
generous that might not work? Where if
it didn't work, only three people would
know.
And that's how I grew up. That's how I
spent the formative years when I my
business was struggling. I was
constantly doing things where if they
might if they didn't work, almost no one
would notice.
And you may have heard me tell the story
about my mom, but I'll tell it again.
My mom was one of the pioneers of museum
stores. She co-founded the Museum Store
Association and the museum at the
Albright-Knox in Buffalo is a great
museum.
It was her full-time gig.
When I was a teenager, she came home one
day on a Friday and she seemed a little
down. I said, "What's wrong?"
She said, "Well, we're doing this thing
tomorrow where she had gotten two
appraisers from Sotheby's to come to the
museum cuz she wanted to get people who
never came to the museum to come.
Buffalo's a working-class town. Bring
what, you know, your grandmother's
candlesticks. We'll tell you if they're
worth anything."
She said, "So, I've made this commitment
to these people
and I'm worried because
what if no one comes?"
And then she turned to me and she said,
"Well, if no one comes, no one will know
that no one came.
>> God, that's such a good line.
>> And it became a mantra for me. And the
next morning we went to the museum and
there were 5,000 people waiting in line.
>> Because it was a generous thing to do.
>> Everyone came out ahead. And if no one
had come, no one would have known.
>> Obviously, Seth talks a lot about
getting unstuck. But for business
owners, stuck isn't always so clear. It
could be another quarter where revenue
is technically up, but cash still feels
tight, hiring is messy, important
decisions somehow lands back on your
desk. That is exactly why we built the
growth boardroom. It's not for people
trying to buy their first business. This
is for owners with a real business who
have real problems and want to get to
the next level of the game without
having to do all the expensive things
yourself. So, what is it? Inside you get
my advisors who help me build my
businesses, operators, our advisory
practice, and systems we use as private
equity to scale your business to the
next level of the game. So, let's say
you're having problems with cash flow.
You want more of it. Or you need to hire
a new player. Or your sales team is a
little bit broken. Or maybe it's the
fact that the business only works when
you're in every meeting. Yikes. Growth
boardroom is going to help you fix that.
You join us for 1 year of advisory and
we help you turn the tables on your
business revenue, growth, and profits.
Also, this unfortunately is not for
everybody. If you own a business and
want to see if you qualify, you can hit
the link below, fill out an application,
and if you're a fit, we'll invite you
out to join our boardroom.
>> So, there's a famous artist. You tell
the story about Jackson Pollock. And uh
you have a story that I love. And it's
in it's in the knot, isn't it? Um can
you tell that story?
>> So, in in the middle of the 1900s,
Jackson Pollock was the most famous
painter other than Picasso in the world.
Certainly the most famous American
painter, cover of Life magazine.
He had 3 years in a row where every
single thing he painted sold instantly
and today is worth tens of millions of
dollars.
And um
then he stopped. And he went back to his
studio in Long Island
and started painting a totally different
kind of work. Different scale, different
look.
And his wife, Lee Krasner, who also an
artist, said that he had decided he had
gone as far as he could with what he had
done before at the drip paintings. And
he didn't want to do be like a cover
band doing
re- rehashes of Jackson Pollock
paintings. He wanted to go back to being
the artist.
And so with all that momentum, with
everything going for him, and we've been
talking this whole time about what do
people do who don't have that, right?
With all that momentum,
he brings the new work out, big show,
and everyone hates it. The critics hate
it, no one buys it. You've probably
never seen any of the paintings. I had
to look really hard to find them. I
don't like them, either.
And
it led to an uh
his drinking increasing, and he ended up
uh dying in a drunken car crash taking
him with him.
Why?
Cuz he wanted two things, not one.
He wanted to be on the edge, to be on
the frontier, to be an artist. And
but it's not and, it's but.
But, he also wanted to be successful,
sold out, and rich.
And because the two things couldn't
happen at the same time, he broke.
And that and and but dichotomy
completely changed my life. Once you
understand that you're carrying all
these buts around, and that the buts are
what are keeping you from doing the
thing you say you want, now you can make
a choice, which is stop saying you want
it and live with the fact that the butt
is there, or get rid of the buts
and turn them into ands. I'm going to
run the marathon and I'm going to get
tired. Not, I'm going to run the
marathon but I don't want to get tired.
And once you add the and, right? I'm
going to buy these sorts of Main Street
businesses and my fancy lawyer friends
aren't going to think I'm fancy.
Great. That goes with it. Part of the
deal.
>> Yeah, it seems like you've got to do
this, too. Like the indoctrination to
not ending up like is that you
have to create things just for you, even
if they tank. I mean, we talk about that
sometimes on this channel. My my
favorite videos that we ever do or my
favorite pieces of content are the ones
where I I'm like, I don't care if
anybody else what like I'm ramped up
about this today. Or um even, you know,
sometimes I'll show them to my husband
or friends and they'll be like, this is
so cringey. I'm like, I love it. I think
it's so fun. I don't care. And I think
if you don't have those every so often,
then you end up like letting other
people drive your life. And I see it a
lot with the algorithms, too. You know,
I was just at this like big YouTube
creator thing and it was the biggest
YouTube creators in the world and I
don't really label myself as
a YouTuber or a podcaster or a whatever.
Or I just think I do stuff that I find
interesting and I like business. Maybe
I'm a business person. But um
it was fascinating cuz they all talked
about how once you get boxed in as like
one type of format, one type of video,
it's really hard to break out of that.
But then you start becoming sort of a
mirror to everybody else's desires
instead. And that seems super dangerous.
>> Yes, but we got to be clear
about the choices and the consequences.
They called me up a bunch of years ago
when it was first starting and they
said, "Will you audition for Shark Tank?
We want you to be one of the judges on
Shark Tank."
And I said, "Well, what what do you
think?" And they said, "Well, you would
be the nasty judge."
>> [laughter]
>> And they actually have a bald nasty
judge now, but you would be the nasty
judge.
>> It's Kevin, right?
>> I'm not saying [laughter] anything.
>> I know Kevin. So, I can give him crap.
>> And um
I said to myself, there's a real cost to
that.
If you want the prizes that come from
that,
you have to pay the price that comes
from that.
So, in your case, there's an alignment.
There are a few people who when you like
it, they like it.
And that's great, but if you want to be
Oprah, you can't do that.
Because Oprah has to do things that
large numbers of people are going to
like.
So, the thing you're not allowed to do
is become entitled.
When you're entitled, you've just added
the butt. I want to do exactly what I
want to do, but I want lots of people to
like it. No, can't have it both ways.
>> How many of your books that you wrote
were
I want to do this, don't care what
anybody else thinks as opposed to I
think this is a huge book, and so I'm
going to do it?
>> I've never written a book
that was supposed to be a huge book.
>> Wow, never?
>> I tried when I was a book packager. I
did the Beardstown Ladies Common Sense
Investment Guides. Those were very, very
big books. They were on I had four of
them on the New York Times Best Sellers
at the same time. But that wasn't my
book. I was helping somebody else make
their book.
Uh even though you know, I touched all
of it, their name was on it. The um
the thing is that it's very hard to make
something
knowing it's going to be big.
Now, there is a book I wrote called
Survival Is Not Enough, and Charles
Darwin wrote the forward, which is not
easy cuz he's dead. And
I was indulging myself with that book. I
spent a full year, 8 hours a day. I
wrote 200,000 words
because I could,
and
the book didn't sell. And I don't talk
about the book on stage cuz every time I
talk about it, people's eyes glaze over.
You Evolution is just not a good thing
to talk about on stage cuz it confuses
people.
Okay, fine. Right?
But I didn't completely get kicked out
of the industry, either. I got mostly
kicked out of the industry cuz that was
the consequence of writing a book that I
was just indulging myself. So, when
Purple Cow came out, I didn't have a
publisher.
And I published it myself in a milk
carton for only 5,000 people
because I was writing it for them.
I didn't write that book for me. I wrote
that book for them. And so, ever since
then, I have never written a book for
me.
I try to imagine who are What's the
minimum smallest viable audience
that would be enough?
Is that number
commensurate with what I'm going to put
into it or what my partner's going to
have to cuz if it doesn't match, then
I'm being indulgent. But, if it does
match
if you can satisfy that smallest viable
audience
and you know, in the case of a
a landscaping business, it's six blocks
in the suburbs. If those 500 people
think you're the best there ever was,
it's enough.
And that's the goal is where can we find
that smallest viable audience? There's a
a little shop in Brooklyn called 69
Atlantic and The Art of Play. It's
smaller than this studio.
And they sell little puzzles and things
in the front, and then there's a secret
door in the back. Don't tell anyone I
told you. And
two or three nights a week, they open a
bookshelf and there's a little room
behind it that has 24 seats. And the
greatest magicians in the world come to
this room with 24 people in it.
It's totally worth going.
And if it was 240 seats, none of it
would work.
It's the right number of people in the
right room for the right reason. That's
enough. Just figure out what your enough
is. It might be a million. Right? If
you're on YouTube and you don't have a
million, you're not going to make a
living.
But, there's 8 billion people in the
world. A million's not that many. I know
a guy who does You know those reaction
videos?
>> He does
He and his partner who do who is a
songwriter
both from uh the Midwest do reaction
videos to Filipino pop songs.
>> [laughter]
>> And they did a couple at the first cuz
it was funny cuz they don't understand
the words or anything.
But the Filipino audience found them.
And they make a full-time living doing
this cuz they found their people. That's
what the internet's for. It's a terrible
mass medium. It's a very good micro
medium.
>> It's really freeing when you think about
it that way because you can make money
doing just about anything. And there's a
lot of downsides that come with really,
really big. It's just increasing
complexity. So I always think like, you
know, what a beautiful thing it is that
and you've talked about this in many
ways. You've talked about this like
minimally viable group of people often
in your books, which is really freeing.
And then, you know, Kevin Kelly's got
his thousand true fans. And I think
those two models can really help small
businesses who can make millions or tens
of millions off of a very small subset
of people.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, we have you know, we get 130
million views a month. But the people
that I actually sell anything to is
probably
3,000 or 5,000 people a year. That's not
very many people actually.
>> and they would all miss you if you were
gone.
>> Uh-huh. Yeah.
>> And that's the key. You don't want to
hustle people who wouldn't miss you.
>> Yeah.
>> But if you're offering something to
people who would, they say thank you.
>> It's so freeing because, you know, you
want to like everybody to like you. It's
that high school mentality. I think um
one other thing I want to talk about
from you is you talk about you have this
line that I love. The stickiest
entanglements don't feel like traps.
They feel like facts.
First, can you sort of define what is
entanglements? And then, what do you
mean by that?
>> Right. So entanglements are at the heart
of everything we've just talked about.
They're invisible
action at a distance. They are the
magnetic forces that undermine what
we're doing.
They are the
high school teacher we're still trying
to prove was wrong in what they said
about So there's the old girlfriend who
doesn't even know we exist anymore. They
are the uh memory we have of getting
scolded when we were seven and we don't
want to get scolded again. We are
entangled with all of these feelings.
Spooky action at a distance. They're not
in the room, but they are. We you know,
we paid uh $300,000 to go to dental
school.
Our family supported us. We made it
through and years later we hate being a
dentist. And so now we're going to spend
the next 50 years drilling kids' teeth
because we are entangled with a decision
we made 15 years ago.
We don't have to do that.
We can say
it's true that happened and I forgive
myself or I forgive whatever else can
along because these aren't facts. These
are just things we are choosing to focus
on. And when we watch people who are
excellent at what they do
in any field
it's because they figured out as a
professional how to get unentangled with
that other thing that holds everybody
else back.
And my argument is the secret to dealing
with it is three words.
Tell the truth.
If you tell me the truth about your
entanglements,
they wither in the sunlight
because they're so absurd when we say
them out loud. If we keep saying them
out loud, oh thanks for offering me to
do that, but I remember when I was nine
this thing happened so I'm afraid to go
to this conference cuz it might happen.
What? Right? Tell the truth at work.
When we're entangled at work, like why
do we have this weekly meeting every
Thursday?
Well, we need to have a meeting. No, we
don't have to have a meeting. We could
just have a memo. Why do we have this
meeting every Thursday? Well, uh Oh,
because
the boss likes it if we all sit in a
circle, shake our heads and agree with
her. Okay, now we're clear about why
we're having the meeting, we can make a
new decision based on that truth.
>> Why is it so hard for people to tell the
truth?
And how do you tell yourself the truth
about these situations?
>> Entanglements
are very good at preserving themselves.
That's why they're still around.
So, they come up with an enormous number
of reasons to keep us from doing it. My
friend Steve Pressfield calls this
resistance. Resistance is the invisible
force that, for example, invents
writer's block. No one has writer's
block. Writer's block is a myth.
You
don't get talker's block. No one goes
So, write down what you say. You're
done. You wrote. Now, it might not be
good, but you didn't say you have a
shortage of good writing. You just said
you can't write. So, show me all your
bad writing.
And if you keep doing enough bad
writing, something good is going to
sneak in there. I'm sure of it.
So, resistance is everywhere you look.
It's the parts inside of us, the tender
parts, the scared parts, the little kids
who are protecting themselves in a
shell, who are hiding and fighting
overtime
to force you to sabotage what you say
you want
to protect themselves. And if we can
tell the truth about why you're going to
a singles bar instead of building a real
relationship, why you're eating that
instead of going to go for a walk,
whatever it is,
if we can be clear about it,
it will wither and die. It will always
be something we're aware of, but you can
make a difference for people if you care
enough
to do this work.
Every problem is solvable.
>> So, in practice, how would that work?
Like I remember I sat with Tony Robbins
and I was like I was trying to, you
know, with him I'm like, I want to see
him in action, you know? So, I'm like
So, like I I want to give him something
that I'm bad at or struggling at and
have him fix me, you know? Like isn't
this what what we do here? And um he was
so funny because at the time it was um
I was trying to drink less wine. Like it
doesn't make I'm older this is the
lamest thing ever, but it's just what
was on top of mind for me. I'm I'm
getting older. It doesn't sit that well
with me. I love red wine though. Like I
I love the whole thing about it. And um
you know, so I just would end up
drinking a glass or two every night as
part of my process. And it was very
funny cuz I told him that and he like
looks at me, you know, and he's we've
talked about he's very intense, but in
that moment he's like, "Ah, honey, you
just don't have a big enough why?" And
then he kind of like carries on into the
next thing. And I thought about that for
a while and I was like, "Why don't feel
fixed?" So I'm not sure, you know, what
happened here. And then I I thought
about it later and
since then my husband and I have been
focusing on fertility, which is a big
why. And lo and behold, I'm not drinking
anymore. And it's not even a problem.
And so I was wondering in your take,
like sometimes I hear these things like
we need to find our truths, but they
they are hidden. They hide. And they're
really smooth talkers.
>> Yeah.
>> So let's say somebody right now is
struggling with I feel stuck in creating
my thing, my art, my work, whatever.
How would you poke them to get to the
reason why they're
to the to the story that they're telling
themselves basically?
>> Yeah. Well, Tony is brilliant at this
and I am not.
My my take is you should poke yourself.
>> Mhm.
>> And cuz I'm not going to be in the room
for very long and you can have some
things that you can approach. So, what
we see when we get stuck is stuck is
another word for comfortable.
And we build all sorts of habits to keep
us stuck because we want to be stuck cuz
it's comfortable.
So if we want to undo habits, the best
way to do it is not to constantly
require willpower, but to build new
habits.
A blog post every day is a habit.
So, if you tell me that you want to do
this, and I'm
going to take you at your word that
you're serious about it.
Let's explore where the entanglements
are. Well, I I don't like criticism. I'm
worried that I'll get fired from my job.
I I'm afraid that if I do this, no one
will come. Okay, great.
If you did it under another name,
how many of those problems go away?
Because what you were saying is you want
to create a work, and you want to get
credit for it. Those are two different
things. So, the but was a problem, cuz
it wasn't really an and. If you were
willing to not get credit for it,
would it be easier for you to do
creative work?
So, let's make a habit. There's going to
be a blog post every single day for 4
weeks.
Doesn't have your name on it. There's
absolutely no downside.
If you come back here in 4 weeks, and
you haven't done it, then you don't want
to do the work. But if you do the work,
a month from now, you're a blogger. A
month from now, you're a writer. A month
from now, you're somebody who's written
3,000 words.
And your next 3,000 are going to be
better.
But what you were really saying is that
you want to be Cody, and you want 130
million view without doing Yeah, you of
course you're not going to get that.
But let's discover how do you become the
kind of person
who does this. The kind of person that
when they look in the mirror, sees
someone who does things like this. When
I am in public, I am playing the role of
Seth Godin. I'm not really Seth Godin.
I know what that role is like. I know
how to act that role, but that's a
choice.
So, you become that by
forgiving the entanglements, letting go
of the person you've become habituated
to be.
And instead, make one decision, and turn
it into a series of habits. And if
you're willing to do this work, I've
never once heard from someone who did
the work and didn't get the output.
But you might not be willing to do the
work, and that's fine. It's fine with
me.
>> Do you take off the yellow glasses when
you're not Seth Godin? Like what's the
one what what's the what's the superman
to you know Clark Kent?
>> So one thing I found, I used to go to
TED a lot. Um
people don't
believe it, but most TED speakers are
introverts.
That they don't walk into a cocktail
party and shake hands with every single
person.
And so most of the time I'm sitting in a
room by myself with my puppy, and I'm
writing or I'm thinking or I'm talking
to Claude or whatever it is, but I'm not
like
that. I mean, I think Tony's like that
all the time, but most of the people who
do what we do
we're not like that all the time.
>> Yeah. No, I'm the same. I actually it
gives me anxiety. Although I'm very loud
on the internet, but my husband is
actually the one when we go out in
public, he's great. You know, I call my
front man because he gets to go have all
the action, talk to everybody, and I
kind of chill. I like to think about
things, which is probably why we up on
the internet or write books. You know,
I'm I'm actually quite comfortable with
that. I just feel like there's some sort
of service that comes from sharing it
with other people then I get those
feedback loops.
>> Yeah.
>> I want you to tell the story um that
goes with this quote that I got to put
on the wall, which is
instead of wondering when your next
vacation is, maybe you should set up a
life that you don't escape from.
Very poignant, especially today when for
a lot of people that is possible. You
know, that especially in the US, pretty
possible. And you open up with a parable
about a man named Alexander and the
knot, and I thought there was a lot of
similarity between the two. So would you
mind telling that story?
>> So they call him Alexander the Great. I
think when he was 17, no one added the
great part. He was just Alexander. And
there was a legend in a small town in
Turkey that uh
there was a an ox cart that was tied
with a very complicated knot to the edge
of town and it was said that whoever
could come and untie this knot would
become the ruler of all of Europe.
And uh
Alexander showed up and there's
a myth about it that's not true which is
that he took out a sword, cut it in half
and said, "There's no knot." That's not
really what the story was. The story was
this.
He showed up, he heard the story, he saw
the complicated knot and he said, "Wait,
there's a wooden post in the middle of
it.
If I just pull this post out,
the knot sort of takes care of itself."
Because it had
entwined itself and was concealing the
real problem. Pull out the post and the
knot gets fixed.
That doesn't mean it's easy. It takes a
lot of practice to realize where is the
post, where is the entanglement, where
is the thing I'm going to pull out.
But we're surrounded by knots. There are
all these people who want us to be
mildly unhappy. There are all these
people who want us to measure the wrong
things and buy solace in the form of a
bottle or a fast food or whatever it is.
That's good for them to make us
reasonably unhappy
all the time.
But when you see where the post is and
you see where the knot is, you can make
different choices.
Now the quote you shared is from the
beginning of my book Linchpin
which I wrote 20 years ago, 15 years
ago.
And the world has changed since then. It
has made it harder for freelancers and
for people who had a a day job to find
joy in their work because they basically
have mechanized everything and turned us
into keystroke counting cogs.
But there's still an attitude shift that
goes on.
And it was I'm not good at jet lag. It
was 4:00 in the morning. I'm sitting in
the lobby of this hotel when I'm on
vacation. And [snorts]
my family's asleep, what am I going to
do?
And I'm checking my email and I'm
enjoying it because no one's telling me
what to do. I get a chance to do it.
And these two people walk by. I don't
know why they were up at 4:00 in the
morning and one turns to the other and
says, "Look at that poor man working on
vacation."
And I said to myself, "Look at those
poor schmoes.
They're going to spend 51 weeks unhappy
so they can come here for 1 week a year
and escape."
So, wouldn't it make more sense to make
difficult choices about why we're
spending our time this way? What's
important to us? Do I really want to be
a millionaire or do I just want to tell
people I'm a millionaire? Right? Because
what would make a good life? What is my
purpose? What am I keeping track of? Cuz
if you make $30 million and your family
doesn't speak to you, I don't think you
won.
And I get that Goldman Sachs wants you
to make $30 million cuz that's the only
way they get clients. But that might not
be what you want. So, let's get
unentangled and clear. Tell the truth
about the change we seek to make. Who's
it for and what's it for? Cuz when we
bring this intent
to the work, we might fail and we have
to own that or we might succeed.
But at least we're just not coasting
along as a victim.
>> So, this book and this conversation that
we've had today, what do you hope that
people get when they read The Nudge?
Like when they're done, it's the last
page, they've read through it, what will
have changed in their life?
>> I tell a bunch of stories in the book
about tuberculosis.
And I tell stories about homelessness
and mass transit, big, big, big
problems.
And I talk about little tiny annoying
problems like who won't who loads the
dishwasher.
>> [snorts]
>> And
problems can be solved.
Situations cannot.
If you have a situation,
accept it. Doesn't mean it's fair,
doesn't mean it's right, but that's not
worth your time.
Gravity, you're not going to be able to
do anything about gravity.
But if it's a problem and you can solve
it and make things better for yourself
and other people, I hope you will.
We're not going to run out of problems
anytime soon.
We are running out of optimism, we're
running out of enthusiasm, we're running
out of the ability
to lean into the work.
>> Mhm.
>> And
I'm naive enough to think that maybe if
I wrote a book about that it would help.
>> Well, it's a beautiful book. Seth Godin,
thank you so much for being here today.
>> Thanks, Cody.
>> [music]